<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<chapter xml:id="brachistochrone" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">


<title>The brachistochrone problem</title>

  <section xml:id="sec-brachistochrone-overview">
    <title>The brachistochrone problem: its significance as an illustration</title>
    <p>
      The brachistochrone problem is historically the most interesting of all the special problems mentioned in Chapter I since as we have there seen it gave the first impetus to systematic research in the calculus of variations. Since the time of the Bernoulli brothers it has been used with great regularity as an illustration by writers on the subject, and it is in many respects a most excellent one. Unfortunately in the forms originally proposed by the Bernoullis it does not require the application of an important necessary condition for a minimum which was first described by Jacobi in 1837, more than a century after the calculus of variations began to be systematically studied. A special case of this condition is the restriction on the position of the center of curvature in the problem of finding the shortest arc from a point to a curve, as described in the theorem on page 33 of the last chapter. It is perhaps at first surprising that the significance of such a simple instance of the condition escaped the early students of the calculus of variations, but a study of the older memoirs soon impresses one with a realization of the serious difficulties encountered with the methods originally used. Throughout the eighteenth century, investigators in the calculus of variations for the most part desisted when they had found the forms, or in many cases the differential equations only, of the minimizing curves which they were seeking.
    </p>
    <p>
      It is natural at first sight to suppose that a straight line is the path down which a particle will fall in the shortest time from a given point 1 to a second given point 2, because a straight line is the shortest distance between the two points, but a little contemplation soon convinces one that this is not the case. John Bernoulli explicitly warned his readers against such a supposition when he formally proposed the brachistochrone problem in 1696. The surmise, suggested by Galileo's remarks on the brachistochrone problem, that the curve of quickest descent is an arc of a circle, is a more reasonable one, since there seems intuitively some justification for thinking that steepness and high velocity at the beginning of a fall will conduce to shortness in the time of descent over the whole path. It turns out, however, that this characteristic can also be overdone; the precise degree of steepness required at the start can in fact only be determined by a suitable mathematical investigation. 
    </p>
    <figure xml:id="fig-11">
      <caption>A cycloid generated by a rolling wheel.</caption>
      <image xml:id="img-cycloid" source="images/fig-cycloid.png">
        <description>A cycloid generated by a rolling wheel.</description>
      </image>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The first step which will be undertaken in the discussion of the problem in the following pages is the proof that a brachistochrone curve joining two given points must be a cycloid. We are familiar with the cycloid as the arched locus of a point on the rim of a wheel which rolls on a horizontal line, as shown in <xref ref="fig-11"/>. It turns out that the brachistochrone must consist of a portion of one of the arches turned upside down, and the line on the under side of which the circle rolls must be located at just the proper height above the given initial point of fall.
    </p>
    <p>
      When these facts have been established we are at once faced by the problem of determining whether or not such a cycloid exists joining two arbitrarily given points. Fortunately a modification by Schwarz (1845-1923) of a method due to the Bernoulli brothers will enable us to prove that two points can always be joined by one and but one cycloid of the type desired. 
    </p>
    <p>
      When these results had been attained the eighteenth-century student was content with his progress, but we cannot be so easily satisfied because we know that in other problems of the calculus of variations further conditions on the minimizing arc are required which are quite different in character from those which have so far been described. Our doubts for this particular problem will be removed, however, by a so-called sufficiency proof which will definitely establish the fact that the time of descent from a given point 1 to a given point 2 on a suitably chosen cycloid is shorter than that on every other curve joining those two points. The method used is again that of Weierstrass, a special case of which we have already considered in <xref ref="sec-field"/> of the last chapter. The argument there given and the one which we shall see in the case of the brachistochrone are excellent illustrations of the type of proof which is effective for more general problems of the calculus of variations.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-analytic-formulation">
    <title>The analytic formulation of the problem</title>
    <p>
      In order to discuss intelligently the problem of the brachistochrone we should first deduce for ourselves the integral which represents the time required by a particle to fall under the action of gravity down an arbitrarily chosen curve joining two fixed points 1 and 2. It is agreed that the initial velocity <m>v_1</m> at the point 1 is given in advance, and that the particle is to fall without friction on the curve and without resistance in the surrounding medium. If the effects of friction or a resisting medium are to be taken into account the brachistochrone problem becomes a much more complicated one.
    </p>
    <activity>
      <p>
        I'm hiding the diagram included in the textbook under a little foldy thing. I encourage you to draw your own diagram first, based on the instructions in the next paragraph, and <em>then</em> compare your diagram to the one in the book. (This will actually help you make sense of the book's diagram when you see it, because there's some things that aren't super clear.) Label the following:
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>
              the curve of descent <m>C</m> connecting point 1 and point 2;
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              a moving particle <m>P</m> on the curve <m>C</m>;
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              a tangent line to the curve <m>C</m> at the point <m>P</m>;
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              the vertical and horizontal components of that tangent line;
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              the angle <m>\tau</m> between the horizontal and the tangent line; and
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              the downward force of gravity <m>mg</m>.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </activity>
    <figure xml:id="fig-12">
      <caption></caption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Let <m>m</m> be the mass of the moving particle <m>P</m> in <xref ref="fig-12"/> and <m>s</m> the distance through which it has fallen from the point 1 along the curve of descent <m>C</m> in the time <m>t</m>. In order to make our analysis more convenient we may take the positive <m>y</m>-axis vertically downward, as shown in the figure.
      <aside>
        I always think this is hilarious for some reason. I think I'll try defying gravity!
      </aside>
    </p>
    <p>
      The vertical force of gravity acting upon <m>P</m> is the product of the mass <m>m</m> by the gravitational acceleration <m>g</m>, and the only force acting upon <m>P</m> in the direction of the tangent line to the curve is the projection <m>mg \sin \tau</m> of this vertical gravitational force upon that line. But the force along the tangent may also be computed as the product <m>m \frac{d^2s}{dt^2}</m> of the mass of the particle by its acceleration along the curve. Equating these two values we find the equation
      <me>
        \frac{d^2s}{dt^2} = g \sin \tau = g \frac{dy}{ds},
      </me>
      in which a common factor <m>m</m> has been discarded and use has been made of the well-known calculus formula <m>\sin \tau = \frac{dy}{ds}</m>.
    </p>
    <activity>
      <p>
        That's not a well-known formula to me! Draw yourself a little triangle with angle <m>\tau</m> and sides <m>\Delta s</m> and <m>\Delta y</m>. Use this to conclude <m>\sin \tau = \frac{dy}{ds}</m> in the limit.
      </p>
    </activity>
    <p>
      To integrate this equation we follow a customary procedure and multiply each side by <m>2 \frac{ds}{dt}</m>. The antiderivatives of the two sides are then easily found, 
    </p>
    <activity>
      <p>
        This is honestly just rude because these antiderivatives do take a little work.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>
            Start by writing down the two sides of this equation:
            <me>
              \frac{d^s}{dt^2} = g \frac{dy}{ds}
            </me>
            Multiply both sides by <m>2 \frac{ds}{dt}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            On the RHS, use the chain rule to simplify <m>\frac{dy}{ds}\cdot \frac{ds}{dt}</m>. Then integrate with respect to <m>t</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            On the LHS, some more work is necessary. What does <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m> mean in physical terms? How about <m>\frac{d^2s}{dt^2}</m>? Replace these two things with letters better representing their physical meaning.
          </p>
          <solution>
            <p>
              <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m> means velocity, and <m>\frac{d^2s}{dt^2}</m> means acceleration.
            </p>
          </solution>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            Integrate the LHS with respect to <m>t</m>. You'll need to do a <m>u</m>-substitution. What's a smart choice for <m>u</m>?
          </p>
          <solution>
            <p>
              <me>
                \int 2av\, dt.
              </me>
              If I choose <m>u = v</m>, then <m>du = a\, dt</m>, so the integral becomes
              <me>
                \int 2u\, du = u^2 = v^2 = \left(\frac{ds}{dt}\right)^2.
              </me>
            </p>
          </solution>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </activity>
    <p>
      and since they can differ only by a constant we have
      <men xml:id="eqn-3-1">
        \left(\frac{ds}{dt}\right)^2 = 2gy+c.
      </men>
      The value of the constant <m>c</m> can be determined if we remember that the values of <m>y</m> and <m>v = \frac{ds}{dt}</m> at the initial point 1 at the fall are <m>y_1</m> and <m>v_1</m>, respectively, so that for <m>t=0</m> the last equation gives
      <me>
        v_1^2 = 2g
      </me>
      
    </p>
  </section>
</chapter>
